this vitamin D story is full of
surprises I'm going to walk you through
a number of analyses on how Vitamin D
supplementation affects your bone health
and I think you'll be a little surprised
by the results to start since this is
physionic and since the Mystery Begins
in how Vitamin D interacts with our
bones let's come to some understanding
of the mechanisms before we get to the
clinical data for that we can lean on
these two scientific reviews here in the
researchers point out the fascinating
and complex mechanisms by which vitamin
D affects our bones so buckle up vitamin
D can act directly on your bone cells
through a binding of a nuclear receptor
meaning a receptor found in the cells
that once bound will move to the nucleus
of your cells where your DNA of your
cells is kept here the vitamin D
receptor controls the gene reading known
as transcription of Cal [__] metabolism
bone remodeling bone mineralization and
more the vitamin D receptor not only
directly binds these genes to encourage
or discourage their reading to make the
responsible proteins but it can
influence other signaling proteins
called co-activators and co-repressors
to bind these genes to allow or disallow
the production of those bone remodeling
proteins the amount of vitamin D calcium
and Bone regulating hormones in the
blood influence if vitamin D receptor is
active or not so we've discussed
generically how the vitamin D receptor
works but more specifically it can
influence stem cells in your bones to
turn into different bone cells your bone
cells are split into three camps
osteoclasts osteoblasts and osteocytes
we'll focus on the first two and I'll
even explain what they do
too so osteoclasts are known for being
bone resorption cells meaning that they
degrade at the bone material that's
already present if you're thinking well
shouldn't we stop these cells the answer
is well yes and no yes as in we don't
want them to be overactive but no
because our bones need to be remodeled
continuously and osteoclast carry out
that key function for optimal bone
health as they destroy less than optimal
organization of the bone structure on
the flip side
osteoblast are the bone building cells
these cells deposit bone material like
extracellular Matrix hydroxy appetite
and other protein calcium and phosphate
structures that give material and
strengths to the Bone okay vitamin D
receptors are heavily found on stem
cells that can be convinced to become
osteoblasts when vitamin D binds these
stem cells begin producing osteoblast
differentiation proteins these are
proteins that convince the cell to
become a bone cell like runks 2 osterix
and alkaline phosphatase not only that
vitamin D receptor when Bound by vitamin
D can encourage osteoblasts those are
the bone building cells to produce more
bone related proteins for bone
mineralization bone production that's a
lot but we're actually going to go layer
deeper because so far everything seems
to fall in line with well generally how
we think about vitamin D and Bone but
I'm about to introduce a wrench into the
picture vitamin D receptors can also
influence the production of two key
proteins in osteoblasts rank L and OPG
rank L is an
osteoclastogenic factor which means that
it activates the bone destroying
osteoclast vitamin D receptor is known
to inhib ibit the production of rank l
in osteo blast which would otherwise be
produced and bind the
osteoclasts on their membrane bound rank
protein when rank L on osteoblast and
rank on osteoclasts interact it triggers
immature osteoclast to turn into mature
osteoclast and begin destroying bone the
active vitamin D receptor stops that
from happening by reducing rank L
production but also by encouraging the
production of OPG which binds rank L
itself blocking rank on OC class from
interacting the short of it is vitamin D
receptor encourages bone building and
reduces bone
destruction now what if I told you that
the vitamin D receptor is also known to
do the exact opposite namely that it
increases rank L and reduces OPG with
the overall effect of reducing
osteoblast activity and increasing
osteoclast activity well that's what
this review points out so think to
yourself how can the same molecule
vitamin D increase bone production and
yet also decrease bone production using
the exact same mechanism there is an
answer and we'll get to it first let me
mention that the mechanisms that I just
went over are actually only a few
there's many others like vitamin D
affecting calcium absorption or the
effect on the parathyroid but I focused
on the Direct effects second I'd like to
get into the clinical data because
there's some Mysteries here too but
don't worry I promise we will get some
solid answers okay let's start here in
this analysis the researchers compiled
data from 23 randomized control trials I
really like several aspects of this
analysis because they included a
majority of studies that used an inert
Placebo as the comparison against
vitamin D they also limited the analysis
to include only studies that lasted a
minimum of 6 months which is important
when measuring such a slow growing
system like the skeletal system if we
look at the data here we're looking at
bone density in the lumbar spine note
the studies are listed on the left side
and the Deltas or the difference between
the control and the vitamin Des
supplemented people are on the right
however we can ignore that and look at
the
squares these are the results of each
study as well if they fall on the Zero
line there's no benefit of vitamin D
supplementation on bone density if they
fall to the right there is a benefit
clearly some move to the right and some
move to the left leaving us well equally
confused so to
simplify you can focus on the diamond at
the bottom which is the toal effect all
studies accounted for if you're thinking
to yourself there doesn't really seem to
be an effect you're exactly right
there's no effect of vitamin D
supplementation on bone in fact across
multiple other measures these results
Remain the case however it wasn't
universally the case when measuring the
femoral neck vitamin D supplementation
did offer a benefit still the majority
of the measures indicated no effect
there's several reasons why we'll get
into that first allow me to introduce
you to one more analysis and this
analysis tells a vastly different story
because the majority of the measures
here which are identical to the ones
used in the previous analysis like
femoral neck uh spine bone density
indicate an effect of vitamin D we see
that exemplified here the rules on how
to read this are identical to before the
studies are just a ugly neon green we
can see the overall effects Diamond move
to the right and confirm statistically
that vitamin D supplementation provides
benefit to lumbar spine bone density the
same measure that squarely was not
showing an effect in the previous
analysis so why the
discrepancy I know some are going to
jump to funding of the studies and
conflicts of interest so I looked into
both of those analyses and both were
independent of Industry funding and the
only researcher with ties to industry
was involved in the analysis indicating
vitamin D was effective so we should
look for other key differences between
these analysis for one the second the
more favorable analysis included more
studies 13 more studies in fact however
the inclusion criteria standard for
which studies would be included was set
lower meaning that they included more
studies that were not Placebo blinded
which means the analysis might have more
data to detect effects but it is also
more burdened with the potential bias
however they also included only studies
using vitamin D3 which is believed to be
more potent than D2 the first analysis
included both which would muddy the
waters so it's quite a pickle that we're
in fortunately there are still some ways
of getting the
answer by the way I also looked at
Vitamin D on bone fracture risk and I'm
going to be going over more vitamin D
bone mechanisms in the extended version
of this video if you're interested just
join the physionic Insiders I'll also be
going over specific unaffiliated product
recommendations that are independently
tested for Quality I try to cover it all
for The Insider so consider joining the
link is in the description okay
let's get some answers to all of it if
we group all these data together a few
things stand out one both analyses
indicate that effectiveness of vitamin D
supplementation is most robust in people
who are deficient both groups of
researchers show data that in these
people there is a benefit the second
analysis pointed out four things that
determine Effectiveness one consistent
use two
Baseline vitamin D levels so deficiency
that we just went over three vitamin D
levels at the end of the study so were
people no longer deficient and for sex
women experienced greater benefit than
men and although not as readily agreed
upon by the second analysis the first
analysis indicates that older
individuals over the age of 65
experienced the greatest benefit to
their bones from vitamin D
supplementation so all considered it
seems vitamin D supplementation has more
evidence in its favor than against but
there's some nuances here that we need
to discuss remember when we went over
how Vitamin D increases and decreases
the activation of the osteoclast through
the same mechanism while the researchers
of this more conservative analysis
propose there is a basic response of
vitamin D meaning there are two bodily
reactions to vitamin D one when vitamin
D is too low and one when vitamin D is
too high they argue that having two low
vitamin D levels leads to Greater bone
resorption so greater osteoclast
activity then normal levels allow the
appropriate balance of osteoblast
activity for bone building and
maintenance and then very high vitamin D
levels again lead to Greater osteoclast
activity bone resorption so the dose is
the cure and the poison which means that
supplementation should be done carefully
in fact they point out that vitamin D
shots where people take up to I don't
know 100,000 IUS at once or more of
vitamin D in one go or even if they
consume large amounts on a daily basis
can have unintended bone weakening
effects because of this vitamin D
paradoxical effect on the bone cells
that we
discussed actually there's more to be
said on that front when looking at bone
fractures assuming that you're watching
the extended version so where does that
leave us everything considered here are
the takeaways vitamin D supplementation
is a yes for those who are deficient
it's likely a benefit for people over
the age of 65 however if your blood
vitamin D levels are normal and you're
under 65 the supplementation of vitamin
D is probably not necessary however
assuming a person did want to supplement
most studies including those indicating
Effectiveness use modest doses between
400 and 800 IU of D3 possibly slightly
higher for those over 65 also keep in
mind that we're assessing bone health so
this does not extend to other benefits
of vitamin D anyway want more of this
kind of Investigation of the science
while then check out this next video
thanks for tuning in
[Music]